我们来谈谈什么是好方法，
Let's talk about what makes a good method,
什么是好的规格。
what makes a good spec.
所以它显然应该简洁，简短，清晰，
So it should obviously be succinct, short, clear,
结构良好。
and well-structured.
但它的内容有点难开。
But the content of it is a little harder to prescribe.
没有绝对正确的规则，但这里有一些准则。
There are no infallible rules, but here are some guidelines.
首先，规范应该是一致的。
First of all, the spec should be coherent.
也就是说不应该有很多不同的案子
That means it shouldn't have a lot of different cases
彼此没有关系。
that aren't related to each other.
如果你有很多参数或者你有很深的
If you have a lot of parameters or if you have deeply
在其行为描述中嵌套if语句
nested if statements in the description of its behavior
或者如果您传递的布尔标志
or if you're passing Boolean flags that drastically
改变它的作用，这些都是迹象
change what it does, these are all signs
一个不连贯的规范。
of an incoherent spec.
所以让我们看看这个，例如--
So let's look at this one, for example--
有人发现它应该返回所有指数的总和
some find that says it should return the sum of all indices
在出现该值的数组a和b中。
in the arrays a and b at which that value appears.
这是精心设计的吗？
Is this well-designed?
可能不是。
Probably not.
它试图同时做几件事。
It's trying to do several things at once.
它在a中寻找指数。
It's looking for indices in a.
它在b中寻找指数。
It's looking for indices in b.
然后，把它们加在一起。
And then, it's summing them all together.
最好写两个独立的过程--
It would really be better to write two separate procedures--
在一个数组中查找索引的人
one that finds indices in one array
一个想用这种东西的客户
that a client who wants to use something like this
可以打两次电话，然后打另一个。
can call twice, and then the other one that sums.
这是另一个例子。
Here's another example.
所以这是一个规格，我们实际上
So this is a spec that we've actually
在代码回顾阅读中看到。
seen before in the code reviewing reading.
那么长单词的作用是什么呢，需要一个单词列表
So what count long words does, takes a list of words
它存储了列表中最长的单词
and it stores the longest word on that list
在这个全局变量中最长的单词。
in this global variable longest word.
它还计算元素的数量，
And it also counts the number of elements,
列表中的单词数
number of words in the list that are
大于另一个全局变量，长字长，
greater than another global variable, long word length,
到控制台。
to the console.
所以这又是两件不同的事情。
So this is doing, again, two different things.
它在数单词，它在寻找最长的单词。
It's counting words, and it's finding the longest word.
但它也在做坏事，我们指出
But it's also doing bad things, things that we pointed out
以前都不是很好的方法设计规范。
before are not good design for a specification for a method.
它使用全局变量作为参数
It's using global variables for a parameter
以及返回值的全局变量。
and a global variable for a return value.
它还把东西打印到控制台上
And it's also printing things to the console
而不是退回。
instead of returning them.
所以最好我们在这里分别写两个方法
So it would be better if we wrote two separate methods here
如果我们避免使用这些全局变量。
again and if we avoided use of these global variables.
现在，方法的结果也应该是信息性的。
Now, the result of a method should also be informative.
这里有一个不好的规范没有做到这一点的例子。
And here's an example of a bad spec that doesn't do that.
所以这是一个put方法
So this is a put method that takes
一张地图，一个键和一个值。
a map and a key and a value.
实际上，我们使用的是严格的参数
And we're using, actually, tight parameters here
允许k和v变化。
that allow k and v to vary.
它本质上可以是任何类型的。
It could essentially be any types.
所以k可以是弦。例如，v可以是整数。
So k could be string. v could be integer, for example.
前提条件允许值为空
And the precondition allows the value to be null
并允许映射包含空值。
and allows the map to contain null values.
但它也在其后条件中使用
But it also in its postcondition uses
空值作为特殊返回值。
null as a special return value.
我们之前讨论过
And we talked about this before when we
在谈论例外情况。
were talking about exceptions.
所以这个规格的问题是
So the problem with this spec is that it's
客户无法区分案件
impossible for the client to distinguish between the case
在地图上根本找不到钥匙的地方
where the key wasn't found in the map at all, in which case
由于这个子句，它返回null
it's returning null as a result of this clause
或者在地图上找到钥匙的地方，
of the postcondition, or where the key was found in the map,
但放进去的值是空的。
but the value that had been put in there was null.
所以这将是一个糟糕的设计。
So this is going to be a bad design.
我们真的应该另辟蹊径
We should really find a different way
表示钥匙不在地图上。
to signal that the key is not in the map.
或者更好的是，我们根本不应该使用nulls。
Or even better, we shouldn't really be using nulls at all.
我们要确保我们的规格足够坚固，
We want to make sure that our specs are strong enough,
他们向客户提供足够有力的保证
that they give a strong enough guarantee to the client
在一般情况下，这样客户可以做一些有用的事情。
in the general case so that the client can do something useful.
例如，当
For example, we don't want to throw an exception when
我们有一个错误的论点，但是允许任意的突变
we get a bad argument, but allow arbitrary mutations
直到我们抛出那个例外。
until we throw that exception.
客户将无法确定哪些突变
The client won't be able to determine what mutations
可能是在我们抛出异常之前。
might have actually been made before we threw the exception.
例如，假设我们有一个add all方法
So, for example, let's say we have an add all method that
应该把清单2的元素
is supposed to take the elements on list 2
并将它们附加到列表1中。
and append them to list 1.
所以它对列表1进行了修改，但是附加了
So it's mutating list 1, but with the additional proviso
如果它在列表2中遇到空元素，
that if it ever encounters a null element in list 2,
它将抛出一个空指针异常。
it's going to throw a null pointer exception.
问题是当函数
And the problem with this is that when the function does
抛出空指针异常，
throw that null pointer exception,
它将添加一些任意数量的元素
it will have added some arbitrary number of elements
列表1。
to list 1.
而客户却被忽略了
And the client is left figure out
列表1在列表之前是如何被弄乱的--
how list 1 might have been messed up before the list--
在add之前，all最终抛出了那个异常。
before add all finally threw that exception.
所以这个规格真的不够强，
So this spec is really not strong enough,
没有足够的保证
doesn't give a strong enough guarantee
给愿意接受交易的客户
to the client that will let it deal
除了这个例外。
with this exception sensibly.
一个更好的规范会说如果这些元素中的任何一个
A better spec would instead say if any of these elements
为空，将引发空指针异常
are null, it will throw a null pointer exception
不修改列表1。
without modifying list 1.
这将是一个更强大的规范，但更有用的一个。
And that will be a stronger spec, but a more useful one.
规格也必须足够弱
The spec also has to be weak enough
处理不可避免的情况。
have deal with situations that will inevitably arise.
例如，假设我们有一个开放的方法
For example, suppose we have an open method that
接受一个文件名并返回一个字符串。
takes a file name and is supposed to return a string.
后条件只是说
And the postcondition simply says
它打开一个名为file name的文件。
it opens a file named file name.
这是一个不够强烈的后置条件。
This is not a strong enough postcondition.
它告诉我们的还不够多
It's not telling us enough about what
文件--文件的打开方式。
file-- how the file was opened.
它不能告诉我们发生了什么——无论
It doesn't tell us what happens when-- whether or not
文件存在，如果不存在，是否创建该文件。
the file exists, whether it gets created if it doesn't exist.
事实上，它太强了
And in fact, it's actually too strong
因为它无法保证
since there's no way that it can guarantee that it's going
成功打开文件。
to succeed at opening a file.
当您试图打开真正的文件系统时，它们可能会失败。
Real file systems can fail when you try to open them.
他们可能——你可能没有打开那个文件的权限。
They may-- you may not have permission to open that file.
文件系统可能已满。
The file system may be full.
可能还有其他问题
There may be some other problem with it
这基本上是实现者无法控制的
that is basically beyond control of the implementer
这种公开的方法。
of this open method.
所以这个规格真的要说一些更弱的东西。
So this spec really has to say something much weaker.
它不得不说它试图打开一个文件。
It has to say something like it attempts to open a file.
如果成功，则它打开的文件具有某些属性。
If it succeeds, the file that it opened had certain properties.
规范也应该在Java中使用抽象类型
A spec should also in Java use abstract types
只要可能。
wherever possible.
记住在Java中，我们可以使用这些接口，
So remember in Java, we can either use these interfaces,
比如列表和集合，或者特定的实现，
like list and set, or specific implementations,
比如数组列表和散列集。
like array list and hash set.
如果我们使用接口，抽象接口类型
If we use the interfaces, the abstract interface types
将给客户端和实现者更多的自由。
will give more freedom to both the client and the implementer.
所以这将是一个糟糕的选择。
So this would be a bad choice.
所以这个规范颠倒了一个列表。
So this spec reverses a list.
它接受，它要求调用者向它传递一个数组列表
And it takes in, it requires the caller to pass it an array list
并要求实现者返回数组列表。
and requires the implementer to return an array list.
它们比我们真正的
And these are stronger than we really
必须这样做，因为可能有其他选择--
need to do because there might be alternatives--
有列表的替代实现
there are alternative implementations of the list
客户端可能要传入的接口。
interface that the client might want to pass in here.
这迫使他们把它们转换成一个数组列表
And this is forcing them to convert them into an array list
在归还之前。
before returning them.
同样，实现者是
And similarly, the implementer is
必须在结果中使用数组列表。
obligated to use an array list in its result.
因为这里的行为不取决于
Since the behavior here doesn't depend
关于数组列表工作方式的任何细节--
on anything specific about the way array list works--
这完全取决于事实
it really only depends on the fact
它是一系列有序的物体--
that it's an ordered sequence of objects--
我们可以用这里的t列表和这里的t列表。
we could use list of t here and list of t here.
这将是一个更好的规格。
And that would be a better spec.
另一个设计问题是
Now, another design issue is whether we
想用一个先决条件，如果是，
want to use a precondition and, if so,
方法是否应该实际尝试确保
whether the method should actually attempt to make sure
先决条件在它实际尝试之前就已经满足了
the precondition has been met before it actually tries
做该做的事。
to do what it's supposed to do.
最常用的先决条件
The most common use of preconditions
就是要求一个客户满足
is to demand a property-- demand that a client satisfy
正是因为它会
a property precisely because it would
实现者很难检查它。
be hard for the implementer to check it.
现在，在我们要求
Now, we have to think carefully before we require
一个非常重要的先决条件，因为
a non-trivial precondition because it's
给客户带来不便。
an inconvenience to the client.
他们必须确保
They have to ensure that they don't
调用处于错误状态的方法
call the method in that bad state that
违反了先决条件。
violates the precondition.
因为如果他们这样做了，记住，所有的赌注都是不可能的。
Because if they do, remember, all bets are off.
方法实现可以做任何事情。
The method implementation can do anything.
客户不可能
There's no predictable way that the client
可以从错误中恢复。
can recover from that error.
所以如果他们不满足的话就会变成一个虫子。
So it would become a bug if they didn't satisfy.
所以方法的客户实际上并不喜欢先决条件。
So clients of methods don't actually like preconditions.
如果您查看Java API，公共类和方法
If you look at the Java API, the public classes and methods
在Java API中，他们倾向于不使用前置条件，
in the Java API, they tend not to use preconditions,
但是指定为后置条件
but instead specify as postconditions
当争论不好的时候
that when the arguments are bad, they're going
抛出某些例外。
to throw certain exceptions.
这种方法更容易失败。
This approach makes it much easier to fail.
快让我们更容易找到
Fast makes it easier for us to find
调用方代码中的错误或错误假设，
bugs or incorrect assumptions in caller code,
而不是让那些坏的值通过程序传播。
rather than let those bad values propagate through the program.
但有时检查病情是不可行的
But sometimes it's not feasible to check a condition
没有使方法变得令人无法接受的缓慢。
without making a method unacceptably slow.
那是我们想要先决条件的时候。
And that's when we want to use a precondition.
例如，如果我们想使用
So, for example, if we wanted to implement the find method using
二进制搜索而不是线性搜索，
binary search instead of linear search,
我们需要对数组进行排序。
we would have to require that the array be sorted.
如果我们强制使用find方法
And if we forced the find method-- the implementer of the
find方法来实际检查数组是否已排序，
find method to actually check that the array is sorted,
这将挫败二进制搜索的全部目的。
that would defeat the entire purpose of the binary search.
我们必须——二进制搜索的目的是
We would have to-- the purpose of the binary search is to get
对数时间的结果。
the result in logarithmic time.
并检查数组是否已排序
And checking that the array is sorted
需要线性时间搜索。
would require a linear time search.
所以我们想用一个先决条件
So we would want to use a precondition
为了那种寻找方法。
for that kind of find method.
现在，决定是否使用先决条件
Now, the decision whether to use a precondition
是一个工程判断。
is really an engineering judgment.
关键的因素是检查的成本
The key factors are the cost of the check in both the execution
在这里是相关的
of the code, which is what is relevant here
在二进制的查找方法中，也在编写成本中
in the find method of binary, but also in the cost of writing
代码并在客户端上维护
the code and maintaining it both on the client's
一方和实施者的一方。
side and the implementer's side.
判断的另一部分是程序的多少
Another part of the judgment is how much of the program
使用这种方法。
uses that method.
如果它只在类中本地调用，
If it's only called locally in a class,
事实上，如果这是一个班级的隐私，
in fact, if it's private to a class,
然后我们可以检查它的前提条件
then we can check its precondition
仔细观察所有调用该方法的地方。
by looking carefully at all the places that call the method.
我们可以推断前提条件会得到满足。
And we can reason that the precondition will be satisfied.
但如果方法是公开的
But if the method is public and if it
可供同一程序中的其他开发人员使用
could be used by other developers in the same program
或者即使它在一个库中，而其他开发人员可能
or even if it's in a library and the other developers might
写他们自己的程序，然后
be writing their own programs, then it
使用先决条件可能不太明智。
would probably be less wise to use a precondition.
我们应该使用Java API类方法
And we should instead use the Java API class approach
抛出异常。
of throwing exceptions.
现在，我们几乎所有的方法都在使用public
Now, we've been using public for almost all of our methods
没有认真考虑过。
without really thinking about it.
决定一个方法是公开的还是私有的
The decision about whether to make a method public or private
实际上是关于合同的决定
is actually a decision about the contract
整个班级的规格
of the whole class, the specification
在全班同学中。
of the whole class.
其他部门可以自由使用公共方法
Public methods are freely accessible to other parts
计划的一部分。
of the program.
如果你把它公之于众，那就是把它作为一种服务来做广告。
If you make it public, you're advertising it as a service.
你承诺提供这项服务
And you're committing to providing that service
从这里开始。
from here on out.
如果你把你所有的方法都公之于众--
If you make all of your methods public--
这不是个好主意——包括
this is not a great idea-- including helper methods that
只在本地使用，
are really only meant for local use,
然后程序的其他部分可能会依赖于它们。
then other parts of the program may come to depend on them.
那会让你更难
And that will make it harder for you
内部实施的变化
to change in the internal implementation
你将来的班级。
of your class in the future.
你的代码还没准备好修改
Your code won't be as ready for change
如果你只是一味地公开一切。
if you just blindly make everything public.
同时公开内部助手方法
Making internal helper methods public also
为类提供的接口添加混乱。
adds clutter to the interface your class offers.
如果你把那些内在的东西保密，
If you keep those internal things private,
你的类的公共接口将
your class' public interface will
更小更连贯
be smaller and more coherent, which
意味着对其他程序员来说
means it will be easier for other programmers
去理解。
to understand.
我们会看到一些更有力的理由
We're going to see some stronger reasons to use private
当我们谈到抽象数据类型时，
when we talk about abstract data types,
当我们开始编写
when we start to write classes that
具有持久的内部状态。
have persistent internal state.
保护这个国家
Protecting this state using private
将有助于保护我们的程序不受错误的影响。
is going to help keep our programs safe from bugs.
所以访问控制对这三件事都有好处
So access control is good for all three things
我们在这堂课上所关心的。
that we care about in this class.
我们几乎所有的方法都使用了static，
We've also been using static for almost all of our methods,
再说一次，没有太多的讨论。
again, without much discussion about it.
静态方法没有关联
Static methods are not associated
一个类的任何特定实例。
with any particular instance of a class.
你叫他们上课
You call them on the class itself
while实例方法，它们是
while instance methods, which are the ones that are declared
没有静态关键字，必须是
without a static keyword, must be
对特定对象调用。
called on a particular object.
这就是静态方法和实例之间的区别
That's the difference between static methods and instance
方法。
methods.
现在，实例方法的规范是同样编写的
Now, specs for instance methods are written just the same
作为静态方法的规范，但是
as specs for static methods, but they'll often
引用实例的属性
refer to properties of the instance on which they
我们通常用这个词。
were called, which we usually talk about using the word this.
在Python中，它是self。
In Python, it would be self.
在Java中，我们使用this这个词。
In Java, we use the word this.
所以考虑一下我们的find规范
So thinking about our find specification
它接受一个整数数组和一个整数值
that takes an integer array and an integer value
在数组中搜索它，这是一个静态方法。
and searches for it in the array, that's a static method.
所以不需要对对象调用它。
So it doesn't need to be called on an object.
所有参数都在这里。
All of its parameters are right here.
但是如果相反，我们的班级乱七八糟
But what if, instead, we had a class intArray
我们用来存储整数数组的。
that we were using for storing that array of integers.
那么，那个intArray类可能有一个实例方法。
Then that intArray class might have an instance method.
注意，它没有静态关键字
Notice, it doesn't have the static keyword
开始的时候。
at the start of it.
还要注意，它不再使用显式数组
And notice also that it's no longer taking an explicit array
参数。
parameter.
原因是它将被一个对象类型调用
And the reason is it's going to be called on an object type
提供整数数组的无序。
intArray that will provide the array of integers.
所以我们在这里看到的只是剩下的参数--
So all that we're seeing here is the remaining parameters--
在这种情况下，int val。
in this case, int val.
现在，我们谈谈先决条件
And now, we talk about the precondition
就这个对象和后条件而言
in terms of this object and the postcondition
就这个目标而言。
in terms of this object.
再说一遍，这个词“this”就是
And again, this word "this" is what
Java用来谈论
Java uses to talk about the object on which you're
调用实例方法。
calling the instance method.
关于规格我们还有很多话要说
We'll have a lot more to say about specifications
例如，当我们讨论抽象数据类型时的方法。
for instance methods when we talk about abstract data types.